Hi, בוקר טוב *Boker tov*. Today's דף *daf* is כ"ג *chaf gimel*
and we did the משנה mishna, *mishna* yesterday. We started top of
כ"ג *chaf gimel* three lines in. I should mention one thing I
forgot to mention yesterday. We had looked at the whole discussion about
the סכך schach, *schach* at two layers and using an idea of
לבוד lavud *lavud* or חבוט רמי *chavut rami* to combine the two
layers. רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* there emphasized that the problem was that at two different layers,
there was a lot of sunlight. And then in particular the חידוש
*chiddush* is that even when you virtually combine it, even though it's
not really providing shade because in some virtual reality it is, that's
enough. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* makes two interesting points that I failed to
mention. One is that he says we would not judge the question,
this is always the question, how do you judge if it's providing
shade? Where are we assuming the sun is? So תוספות *Tosafot* says
that when we have to measure whether the סכך schach, *schach* provides
shade, we're assuming the sun is directly overhead, not at an angle.
And therefore just in case, well, okay, it could be quite
a bit
as much directly overhead as possible. And תוספות *Tosafot* says therefore if
the sun is directly overhead, even if you have the סכך schach
*schach* at two layers, not as much is getting through. Now again,
let's not get into the whole debate how true that is or
not. But anyway, but the first important point תוספות *Tosafot* makes is
that you judge the issue of shade when the sun is directly
overhead. So he says the issue here is not that the sun
is getting through. The issue here is just can you consider these
two layers to be one סכך schach, *schach* or not? You know,
because each סכך schach. *schach* by itself is not sufficient. They're only
sufficient combined. But they actually are providing shade. But are they one
roof or are they two roofs? And therefore that's what תוספות *Tosafot*
says you need the idea of לבוד lavud. *lavud* or חבוט רמי
*chavut rami*. The reason that's interesting and important is because then
using
the principle from אהלות *Ohalot* where you consider it to be one
אהל *ohel* is much more directly relevant. There's no issue of shade,
we've got the shade covered, excuse the pun,
the shade is fine. The only issue is is it one or
two separate roofs? And therefore these principles for אהלות *Ohalot* are much
more directly relevant. So I just wanted to point out that approach
of תוספות *Tosafot* which makes the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* more simpler. Anyway,
let's take a look now where we pick up on the top
of כ"ג עמוד א' amud aleph. *chaf gimel amud aleph* in the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* three lines down. The משנה *mishna* said that if
you make a סוכה sukka *sukkah* on a wagon or on a
boat, it's כשר *kosher* and you can go up onto it in
יום טוב *Yom Tov* because as opposed to a tree or an
animal where you cannot get into it on יום טוב *Yom Tov*
because you cannot climb a tree or you cannot be climb an
animal, get on use a tree or use an animal on יום
טוב *Yom Tov*. Okay, so first we're going to look at the
issue of the boat or the wagon. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this. מני מתניתין *Mani matnitin*? Who's our משנה *mishna* like?
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva היא *Rabbi Akiva hi*, it's רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva *Rabbi Akiva*. דתניא detanya, *Detanya*, we taught in a ברייתא braita.
*baraita*. עושה סוכה sukka בראש הספינה *Oseh sukkah berosh hasfina*,
let's say you make your סוכה sukka *sukkah* at the top of
a boat.
I always wonder what the word בראש הספינה *berosh hasfina* means. I
guess it means not at a lower level but you know at
the top level of the boat. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel פוסל *Rabban
Gamliel posel*, רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* says it's invalid. רבי עקיבא מכשיר
*Rabbi Akiva machshir*, רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says it's כשר *kosher*. מעשה
*Maaseh*, now there was a story ברבן גמליאל ורבי עקיבא שהיו באים
בספינה
*be-Rabban Gamliel ve-Rabbi Akiva she-hayu va'in basfina*. רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* and
רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* were on a boat. And it was סוכות
*Sukkot*. עמד רבי עקיבא ועשה סוכה sukka בראש הספינה *Amad
Rabbi Akiva ve-asah sukkah berosh hasfina*. רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* got up
and he made a סוכה sukka *sukkah* at the top of the
boat. למחר *Lemachar*, the next day, נשבה רוח *nashva ruach*, the wind
a wind blew, ועקרתה *ve-akratah*,
and it tore down the סוכה sukka *sukkah*. אמר לו רבן גמליאל
*Amar lo Rabban Gamliel*, so רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* said to him,
עקיבא, היכן סוכתך *Akiva, heichan sukkatcha*? עקיבא *Akiva*, where's your סוכה sukkah
*sukkah*? You gotta love
anyway. So of course interesting question is, so what does it mean?
It means that רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*, you know, did they not
dwell in a סוכה sukkah? *sukkah*? I mean I guess not, you
know, I mean it's הולכי דרכים *holchei drachim* which is another interesting
question, right? Why aren't they פטור מן הסוכה *patur min hasukkah* because
of you know of that? Or what we'll see about הולכי דרכים
*holchei drachim* later. But I guess רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* figured look,
I'm not going to be יוצא yotze. *yotzei* with such a סוכה
sukkah *sukkah*, so it's not even worth building it. So you know
you're אנוס onus. *onus*.
כל הנחלים הולכים לים *Kol hanachalim holchim
layam*. Right.
So but you want to learn about רוח *ruach*. No, כל הנחלים
הולכים לים *kol hanachalim holchim layam*. Yeah, but anyway. Okay fine. So
רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* presumably felt that even before the wind came
you would not have been יוצא yotzei. *yotzei*. So let's see why
not. אמר אביי amar Abaye, *Amar Abaye*. דכולי עלמא היכא דאינו יכול
לעמוד ברוח מצויה דיבשה לא כלום *Dechulei alma heicha de'eini yachol la'amod
beruach metzuya deyabasha lo klum*.
Everybody would agree that if you build a סוכה sukkah *sukkah* that
is not strong enough to withstand a normal wind on dry land,
then that's not a סוכה sukkah? *sukkah*. I mean it has to
be דירת ארעי *dirat arai* but not so ארעי *arai* that it
can't that it's completely fragile. So if it can't withstand a normal
wind of the land, then it's not considered a דירה *dirah* at
all. לא כלום *Lo klum*.
What? That sukkahs blow down.
Yeah, blow down. But so that's if it's an unusual wind. So
יכולה לעמוד בשאינה מצויה דיבשה *yachola la'amod beshe'eina metzuya deyabasha* and if
it can withstand even a unusual wind on the dry land, like
a strong wind, דכולי עלמא לא פליגי דכשרה *dechulei alma lo pligi
dechshira*. Obviously if it can withstand even the strongest wind everybody agrees
it's כשרה *kosher*. Those are the two extremes. Can't withstand a normal
and can withstand a strong. The question... The question is the middle
case. היכא פליגי heika peligi what's the debate? היכא פליגי what's the
debate? דיכולה לעמוד ברוח מצויה דיבשה deyekhola la-amod beruach metzuya deyabasha ואינה
יכולה לעמוד ve'eina yekhola la-amod now there's a question of the גרסה.
girsa. Our גרסה girsa is אינה יכולה לעמוד ברוח שאינה מצויה דיבשה.
eina yekhola la-amod beruach she'eina metzuya deyabasha. It can't withstand an unusual
wind on dry land, but if you look to the side, some
have the גרסה girsa ברוח מצויה דים. beruach metzuya deyam. It can't
withstand a normal wind on the sea, which is assumed to be
the same, meaning the assumption is that the winds are much stronger
out in the ocean, and the assumption is that a normal wind
in the ocean is the same sort of strength as a very
unusual wind on the dry land. So can a סוכה sukkah? that
cannot withstand that, is it kosher or not?
רבן גמליאל סבר סוכה דירת קבע בעינן. Rabban Gamliel savar sukka diras
keva ba'inan. You need it to be a permanent structure. וכיוון דאינה
יכולה לעמוד ברוח מצויה דים vekeivan de'eina yekhola la-amod beruach metzuya deyam
and now it explicitly says ברוח מצויה דים, beruach metzuya deyam, if
it can't withstand a normal wind on the ocean, לאו כלום היא,
lav klum hi, it's not good, and even if the wind hasn't
blown yet, even if you're sitting in it, it doesn't count as
a סוכה sukkah, because it doesn't have that strength.
רבי עקיבא סבר סוכה דירת עראי בעינן. Rabbi Akiva savar sukka diras
arai ba'inan. No, it's enough to be a temporary dwelling. וכיוון דיכולה
לעמוד ברוח מצויה דיבשה vekeivan deyekhola la-amod beruach metzuya deyabasha and as
long as it can withstand a normal wind on the dry land,
כשרה היא, keshera hi, it's kosher even if it cannot withstand an
unusual wind on dry land or a normal wind on the ocean.
Now this is a little bit strange because it's one thing if
you build your סוכה sukkah, on dry land and you say, okay,
the סוכה sukkah, is good under normal conditions, but you know, if
there would be a strong wind, it would blow down. So then
you could understand saying, fine, but under normal conditions it'll last, it
only has to be a דירת עראי, diras arai, it's fine. Unless
you really want to call it like a דירת קבע, diras keva,
then you're going to say, oh, but it can't withstand, you know,
unusual winds, and you can't call it permanent because it can't really
last over long periods of time, eventually there'll be a strong wind.
That debate you could understand. But if you're building your סוכה sukkah,
on a boat and you're in the ocean, right? That's very strange,
right, that רבי עקיבא would say, look, since were it on dry
land, it would be able to stand, therefore it's good, even though
right now we're on the ocean and it can't withstand a normal
wind on the ocean. Shouldn't context matter? Shouldn't we say that in
this context you can't call it a דירת עראי diras arai because
it will never stand more than a few hours, you know, never
stand more than a day here on the boat in the middle
of the ocean? So it's very strange the idea that רבי עקיבא
would say since if it were on land it would be a
good enough structure, it remains a good enough structure even in the
middle of the ocean.
רבן גמליאל seems to imply that you can't build a סוכה sukkah
on a ship.
It doesn't seem to imply, he says it. Yeah. I mean you
can build it, you're not יוצא.
Well that's what I mean, yeah. Right.
So he would be saying that if you're taking a trip on
a ship you can't fulfill המצוה של
סוכה.
hamitzvah
shel sukka.
Right, you're an אנוס. Yeah. Okay.
Why is there no תיקו teiku here?
What should the תיקו teiku be? This is a מחלוקת רבי עקיבא
ורבן גמליאל. machlokes Rabbi Akiva veRabban Gamliel.
No, I said, in other words, they're not together. תיקו teiku has
to take you to another level.
No, תיקו teiku is when we ask a question that we don't
have any, like, any evidence to bring to either side. Here we
have no, no, תיקו teiku is not a debate that we can't
be מכריע. makhria. Because a debate that we can't be מכריע, makhria,
fine, we have two opinions, so at least we know what the
positions are. תיקו teiku is we ask a theoretical question and there's
no evidence to bring to get any further than the asking of
the, you know.
So it's not the conceptual מחלוקת, machlokes, it's the application of a
principle to a case.
Or you mean the case and we don't know how to rule.
No, no. You don't use תיקו teiku when you don't know how
to rule. You use תיקו teiku when you say, are we talking
about what would be the case... You tell me a הלכה halakha
and I say, yeah, but what would be if...? You know, what
if this? What if that? So you're like, I don't know, like
there's no evidence, we have no textual sources, we have no analytical
way of getting at it.
But it's not the same as not knowing how to rule,
because not knowing how to rule is that you have a debate.
Because it's just you don't use תיקו. teiku. I mean, you don't
know how to rule is I mean, either one you're sort of
stuck, but תיקו teiku is a word used for when there's no
when it's a theoretical question, it's not something that is two sides
and you can't decide between the two sides. It's a hypothetical and
you don't know how to get any more deeper into addressing the
hypothetical. All right. So anyway, so this is what we have, that
the גמרא Gemara says the debate is that it can't withstand a
normal wind, but again that's a more understandable debate on dry land,
how, you know, how much does it have to be able to
withstand unexpected winds. And it's a little less understandable, you know, in
the case I mean, by the way, you know, when I was
in South Florida, you know, and you have like hurricane season or
whatever, you know, it could be that in that you know, that
would be somewhat similar. At that time of year the normal winds
were very strong winds, you know. So it's funny to think again
that when you're on the ocean and those... the normal winds that
it could still be a כשר *kosher* סוכה Sukkah *sukkah*. But it
is a more understandable debate at least on dry land. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes on, או גבי גמל *o gabei gamal*.
So that was the issue about being on the boat. It's not
exactly clear what the issue was about being on the wagon. רש"י
Rashi
*Rashi* says that it has to do with the fact that also
that the wagon moves around, you know, and it jostles so it's
not so stable.
But anyway, now we move on to the issue about on a
camel or on a tree. It's good but you can't go up
to it on יום טוב *Yom Tov* because you can't use an
animal or use a tree on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מתניתין מני רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir היא *Matnitin
mani Rabbi Meir hi*. Who's our משנה *Mishna*? It's going like רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*. דתניא D'tanya, ותני בברייתא *De-tanya u-tana ba-braita*:
העושה סוכתו על גבי בהמה *Ha-oseh sukkato al gabei behema*.
If you make your סוכה *sukkah* on an animal. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir, מכשיר ורבי יהודה פוסל *Rabbi Meir machshir ve-Rabbi Yehuda poser*. רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says it's כשר *kosher*, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says it's פוסל *poser*. מאי טעמא דרבי יהודה *Mai
ta'ama de-Rabbi Yehuda*? What's the reason of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi
Yehuda*? אמר קרא *Amar kra*, the פסוק *pasuk* says: חג הסוכות תעשה
לך שבעת ימים *Chag ha-sukkot ta'aseh lecha shiv'at yamim*.
You should make for yourself a סוכה *sukkah* for seven days. סוכה
הראויה לשבעה שמה סוכה *Sukkah ha-re'uya le-shiva shema sukkah*.
That only if it's fit for all seven days does it count
as a סוכה *sukkah*. שאינה ראויה לשבעה לא שמה סוכה *She-eina re'uya
le-shiva lo shema sukkah*. If it's not fit for seven days it's
not good. So not fit for seven days means that if you
make it and you can't use it on יום טוב *Yom Tov*,
it's not fit for all seven days. Okay, now it's an interesting
question, let's say you made it during חול המועד *Chol Ha-moed*, right?
That maybe could stand for seven days but it wasn't usable for
all seven days of יום טוב *Yom Tov* because you only made
it during חול המועד *Chol Ha-moed*. So we actually see about that,
we actually have seen that in the past. But here the point
is since it cannot be used on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, it's
not a legitimate סוכה *sukkah*, it's not fit for all seven days.
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*: הא נמי מדאורייתא מחזי חזיא *Ha
nami mi-d'oraita meichaza chazya*.
Now interesting, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't say that רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir *Rabbi Meir* fundamentally disagrees it doesn't have to be fit for
seven days. No, fundamentally he agrees, you're right, it does have to
be fit for seven days. But biblically it is fit to use
on יום טוב *Yom Tov* because there's no biblical problem with going
up a tree or on an animal on יום טוב *Yom Tov*.
רבנן הוא דגזרו בה *Rabbanan hu de-gazru bah*. It's the רבנן *Rabbanan*
who made an edict to not allow going up on a tree
or going on an animal on יום טוב *Yom Tov*. So therefore
just because there's a Rabbinic restriction in your way does not mean
in some, you know, in some abstract sense it is not fit
for all seven days. It is theoretically fit for all seven days,
it's just that the and so from the תורה *Torah*'s perspective it's
a totally כשר *kosher* סוכה *sukkah*, it's just the רבנן *Rabbanan* prevent
me from using it. Again, it's interesting
the
גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* frames it as that they both agree in principle
it needs to be able to be used for all seven days.
Okay, now. עשה לבהמה דופן לסוכה *Asah le-behema dofen le-sukkah*. Let's say
this is making your entire סוכה *sukkah* independent of the animal or
the tree but then well we'll talk about animal for now we'll
worry about tree later, and putting it on the animal. Okay, but
let's say you actually use the animal for one of the pieces
of your סוכה *sukkah*. You use your animal for the דופן *dofen*
of your סוכה *sukkah*. Okay. So, I'm sure they do have a
picture there.
Alright, so what I was doing at the end of the table,
what happened? Okay anyway.
So, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir פוסל ורבי יהודה מכשיר *Rabbi Meir poser
ve-Rabbi Yehuda machshir*. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* says it's no
good, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says it's good. דתניא רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir אומר *De-tanya Rabbi Meir omer*: כל דבר שיש בו
רוח חיים *Kol davar she-yesh bo ruach chayim*. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*Rabbi Meir* used to say: Anything that is alive, אין עושין אותו
לא דופן לסוכה *ein osin oto lo dofen le-sukkah*, you cannot make
it a דופן *dofen* of a סוכה *sukkah*, ולא לחי למבוי *velo
lechi le-mavoi*, or a לחי *lechi* for a מבוי mavoy *mavoi*, right,
let's say you wanted to, I don't know what you would do,
you would take an ape and you'd have it stand, you know,
at the opening of your מבוי *mavoi* and you'd use it as
a לחי *lechi*. Okay.
So, ולא לחי למבוי *velo lechi le-mavoi*. The לחי *lechi* is the
post, you know, at the third wall the מבוי *mavoi*. You need
either a post or a beam. ולא פסין לביראות *velo pasin le-vira'ot*.
פסי ביראות *pasi bi-ra'ot* are the corners. You have a well and
you want to be able to draw from which is a רשות
היחיד *reshut ha-yachid*, draw from the well on שבת Shabbat, *Shabbat*, you
make you don't make walls around it you make like the four
corners of it, you know, two perpendicular, you know, perpendicular angles at
all four corners and that allows you draw from the well. Well
don't use animals for those corners, for those mini walls. ולא גולל
לקבר *velo golel le-kever*. And you cannot use it as a גולל
*golel* for a קבר *kever* which means either like a cover for
the grave or a headstone for the grave, we'll see that's a
whole debate, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* תוספות *Tosafot*, exactly what a גולל *golel*
is. Anyway you cannot use it for any of these things. משום
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi, הגלילי אמרו *Mishum Rabbi Yose Ha-Glili amru*, in
the name of רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yose Ha-Glili* they said: אף
אין כותבין עליו גיטי נשים *Af ein kotvin alav gitei nashim*. You
even can't use it for a גט get *get*. Okay, you go
ahead and you take your animal and you, why bother skinning it
and making קלף *klaf*, just write straight on the animal skin. Okay,
now. What is the reason for all of this? Now to some
degree you would like I mean to some degree you could sort
of say this like philosophically that these things
are like live and they cannot be made into objects. To do
it this way you're basically sort of completely turning them into you
know you're making them you know you're having them serve a function
that's normally served by inanimate things and the type not normally served
by also but that is you know that
completely if they were human beings you would say it
dehumanizes. It de-animalizes them, it completely makes them into objects and removes
their sense of living things. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that's
like from a philosophical perspective, and is that what's true? You could
have come up with a much longer list of things you can't
use them for, right? I'm sure we'd come up with a very
long list of things that we need inanimate objects for for הלכה
*halakhic* purposes, and this list is not all comprehensive. So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is going to have to find more concrete reasons why
these are problems to be used in this context.
And we said צלורא *Tzelora*?
Well, that's clear, but that's because it's not cloth. But okay, anyway,
let's get... גט get *Get* is a bigger חידוש *chiddush*. Okay, so
let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Okay. מאי טעמא
דרבי מאיר *Mai ta'ama d'Rabbi Meir*? What's the reason of רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*? אביי Abaye אמר שמא תמות *Abaye amar shema
tamut*: we're afraid the animal will die. And if it dies, then
it won't... you won't have your עשרה טפחים tfachim. *ten tefachim* or
you won't have your לחי *lechi*. It'll fall on the ground. Okay.
Well, okay, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s about to ask that. Okay, but
anyway, and that doesn't explain all the things, like what's the big
deal if a גט get *Get* is written on it? But for
most of these things, it's partly about its being standing up and
the way it's standing helps create that structure you need, the corners
for the well or the post or the wall for the סוכה
*sukkah*. So if it dies, then you'll lose it. רבי זירא אמר
*Rabbi Zera amar*, רבי זירא *Rabbi Zera* says: שמא תברח *shema tivrach*.
You're afraid it'll run away. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this: Let's see a נפקא מינא *nafka mina*. בפיל קשור *Be-pil kashur*,
if it's a tied-up elephant, there you go. So if it's tied
up, it won't run away. And if it's an elephant, even if
it
dies, its body will still serve as the wall. כולי עלמא לא
פליגי *Kulei alma lo peligi*, nobody would disagree. די נמי מית *Dee-nami
meit*, if it would die, יש בנבלתו י' *yesh binivlato yud*, even
if its carcass will give עשרה טפחים tfachim. *ten tefachim*. And we're
not afraid it'll run away because it's tied up. כי פליגי *Ki
peligi*, when would they debate? בפיל שאינו קשור *Be-pil she-eino kashur*, an
untied elephant. למאן דאמר שמא תמות *L'man d'amar shema tamut*, לא חיישינן
*lo chashinan*. If the only concern is death, so we're not afraid
because even if it dies, you'll still have your עשרה טפחים tfachim
*ten tefachim*. למאן דאמר גזירה gezeira. שמא תברח *L'man d'amar gezera shema
tivrach*, but the one that says we're afraid it'll run away, חיישינן
*chashinan*, we would still be afraid because it's an untied elephant. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, ולמאן דאמר גזירה gezeira שמא תמות ניחוש
שמא תברח *u'l'man d'amar gezera shema tamut neichosh shema tivrach*. It says
wait, that doesn't make sense. Even if you said the reason is
you're afraid it'll die, how could you not be concerned that it'll
run away? You've got an untied animal here. Of course you should
be concerned it'll walk away. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says you
know what, you're right. אלא בפיל שאינו קשור כולי עלמא לא פליגי
*Ella be-pil she-eino kashur kulei alma lo peligi*. Nobody disagrees by an
untied elephant. The one who says maybe it'll die is not only
concerned it'll die. Obviously you have to be concerned it'll run away.
He's just also concerned it'll die. So if it's untied, everybody agrees
it's a problem, everybody is concerned it'll run away. כי פליגי בבהמה
קשורה *Ki peligi be-behema kshura*. The debate is not by an elephant,
which is never going to be a problem if it dies, and
if it's untied everybody agrees it's a problem it'll run away. The
debate is an animal, a normal-sized animal that is tied. למאן דאמר
גזירה gezeira שמא תמות חיישינן *L'man d'amar gezera shema tamut chashinan*. If
you're afraid not only that it'll run away, you're also afraid that
it'll die. So this is a problem, the animal will die and
you won't have your עשרה טפחים tfachim *ten tefachim*. למאן דאמר גזירה
שמא תברח *L'man d'amar gezera shema tivrach*, but if your only concern
is that it'll run away, לא חיישינן *lo chashinan*, we're not. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says everybody has to naturally be concerned it'll
run away, an untied animal. So if it's untied, everybody agrees it's
a problem. If it's tied, that's where the debate is. אביי Abaye
*Abaye* says we're still concerned it'll die and
רבי זירא *Rabbi Zera* says no, we're not concerned it'll die, I'm
only concerned it'll run away, so if it's tied up it's not
a problem. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: ולמאן דאמר גזירה שמא
תברח ניחוש שמא תמות *U'l'man d'amar gezera shema tivrach neichosh shema tamut*.
Okay, so you just got through saying everybody's concerned it could run
away, why isn't everybody concerned it'll die? If your concern is like
רבי זירא *Rabbi Zera* it'll run away, you should also be concerned
it'll die. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no. מיתה misa. לא
שכיחא *Mitah lo shechicha*. Death is not so common. An untied animal,
what's it naturally going to do? It's going to walk away. But
the likelihood that the animal will drop dead on you over this
שבת Shabbat, *Shabbos* or over this סוכות *Sukkos*, whatever you're using the
animal for, is a very distant concern and therefore we do not
have to be concerned about it. Okay.
רבי *Rabbi* Katz likes telling a story about a guy that goes
to the רבי *Rabbi* and says, רבי *Rabbi*, I'm so afraid that
I'm going to die. He says, you don't have to be afraid,
you are. What do you think the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is concerned...
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is posing a theoretical... Why is it not
theoretical? You think they really used animals? What? You think they really...
I don't think they used animals.
First of all, I'll say this, I don't think they used animals,
but I think the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* likes talking about, that's part
of the fun is exploring these hypotheticals. I will say though that
somebody, I think it was Jeffrey Rubenstein at NYU, I think he
wrote a doctoral dissertation where his argument was, I never read it,
but this is what I've understood, where his argument was was that
the reason we
find a lot of
these discussions in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
about like גוד אסיק *gud assik* and גוד אחית *gud achis* and
all these things is that there was a scarcity of building materials
available, so they had to deal... So maybe somebody did say, hey,
here I am, I'm a farmer, I've got whatever I've got all
these sheep around but I don't have any spare lumber. But anyway,
I don't think it was, I think that it was more of
a hypothetical, even though one could imagine that it sometimes did happen
in fact. Okay, but even if it's a hypothetical, then what they're
invoking in the conversation is a level of anxiety as a litmus
test for whether it's stable, whether it's קבע enough or not. Right.
Well, that's a good question. I didn't spell that out, meaning what
is the issue if we are concerned it will die? Meaning we
just got through the idea that if it can't withstand an unusual
wind, is it a good סוכה or not a good סוכה? So
you could say, well, if it might die, that's like that's not
a דירת קבע dirat keva because it could like it's like not
being able to withstand an unusual wind. That's not the way רש״י
Rashi explains it in the גמרא, Gemara although it was only one
place used the word גזירה. And the concern less seems to be
like it's not a stable enough structure because it might collapse, so
you could frame it that way like the גמרא Gemara, about the
wind, but it seems to be more of a concern like the
animal will drop dead and you won't be paying attention and it'll
become פסול pasul and you'll use the סוכה without realizing it's become
פסול pasul or you'll carry in the מבוי without realizing it's become
פסול. pasul. That is the way at least the word גזירה seemed
to indicate and that's the point that רש״י Rashi underscores. But you
do make a very good point, given the גמרא before about the
wind you could have just said the whole סוכה is therefore unstable.
Okay, so the גמרא now says like this: ואיכא ריפקא דביני ביני,
ve'ika rifka de'beini beini, I was waiting for somebody to ask this
question. How could you have used your animal for a wall of
the סוכה? What about the space underneath the body between the legs,
right? So I don't understand, even before it died, how is it
a good סוכה? So the גמרא says דעביד ליה בהוצא ודפנא. de'avid
lei behutza vedafna. Alright, you filled that up with some type of
bushes or whatever, you had some material there between the legs of
the animal that helped make, that helped fill up that gap. So
the גמרא says ודילמא רבע, vedilma rava, maybe it'll crouch down? Okay,
so I still don't get it, says the גמרא, okay, you say
you're not afraid it'll die, maybe it'll crouch down? So the גמרא
says דמתיחא באשלי מלעיל. dematicha be'ashlei mile'eil. So the גמרא says that
no, it's being held up with ropes from above. So basically you've
got this animal, not only is it tied so it doesn't run
away, you're right, but you've got it suspended by ropes so it
doesn't crouch down and you've got the area underneath there filled with
like bushes. So the גמרא now says the obvious question: ולמאן דאמר
גזירה שמא תמות, הא נמי מתיחא באשלי מלעיל? uleman de'amar gezeira shema
tamut, ha nami maticha be'ashlei mile'eil? If you've got it suspended by
ropes, so who cares if it dies? You've got the whole thing
constructed, you got the gap filled, suspended by ropes, who cares if
it dies or not? So the גמרא says no, זימנין דמוקים בפחות
משלושה סמוך לסכך. zimnin demukim befachot mishlosha samuch laschach. Sometimes the animal
will be getting just within three of the סכך, schach okay, it
won't get all the way up to the סכך, schach, meaning the
whole animal
from the ground to the top of the animal is, let's say
seven and a half טפחים. tfachim And then it's within three of
the סכך schach. and you say לבוד lavud. and you get your
whole ten טפחים. tfachim Okay? So sometimes you have that, וכיוון דמייתה,
vekeivan de'maisa, and once it dies, כווצא, kvatza, it'll shrink a little
bit, ולאו אדעתיה, velav adatei, and you won't pay attention. So meaning
it'll get out of
the three טפחים tfachim of
the סכך, schach, you won't be able to say לבוד. lavud It's
interesting it gives the example of לבוד. lavud. You could have just
said the animal is exactly ten טפחים tfachim, with the, you know,
is exactly ten טפחים tfachim, off the ground.
Forget how close it is to the סכך. Right? If it's exactly
ten טפחים and it dies and now it's nine and a half
טפחים off the ground, then you don't have the wall. For some
reason the גמרא gave the scenario, I don't know why it gave
the scenario, but it gave the scenario that here's your animal, okay,
and here you filled it up like this, and you've got it
suspended by ropes, and here's the סכך and the animal is like
seven and a half טפחים, and then there's two and a half
to the סכך, right, because, and so you say לבוד so that
gives you your ten. Right? And then if it shrinks, then you're
not going to be able to say לבוד. But I don't get
why it just didn't say the entire contraption is ten טפחים, and
then if it just shrinks a little bit you lose it, it
doesn't matter how close it is to the סכך. Either way, that's
the point. The point is that it might die and it'll shrink
a little bit. But obviously though, this gets to your point about
how much of a hypothetical this is, because if you have to
actually translate the hypothetical into the real world, you realize it's not
so obvious how you could use an animal for a סכך, what
about the gap, what about if it crouches? And once you've solved
all those problems, then your question is, so then what's the issue
to begin with? Alright, so now the גמרא says like this: by
the way, the point we made before about whether it's גזירה or
not, the two words ולאו אדעתיה velav adatei is indicative. It means
it's not that because that could happen it's not a permanent סוכה,
it means that or it's not a stable enough סוכה, it means
because it can happen you could accidentally, you would not notice and
accidentally. It says like this. By the way, the point we made
before about whether it's a גזרה gezeirah or not, the two words
ולאו אדעתיה v'lav adaiteih is indicative. It means it's not that because
that could happen, it's not a permanent סוכה, it means that, or
it's not a stable enough סוכה, it means because it could happen,
you could accidentally, you would not notice and accidentally eat in it
and not be יוצא. So it's a concern not about whether the
סוכה as a whole could be considered stable, but about whether we're
concerned that you might, you know, it might lead to a problem.
לתקנא, letakna, you're not, you don't pay attention to fix it. Now
that maybe, but also particularly in this case, because it's not obvious
if you didn't have it suspended by a rope and it dropped
dead, you would notice it more. Now that we've created this very
constructed case, it makes more sense why we're concerned that you might
not notice it, because it's not such an obvious difference after it
dies. It looks, oh, looks just as good, it's still suspended. Okay,
I don't know why the guy started complaining about the smell, but
okay. Probably was pretty smelly even before it died. Okay, ומי אמר
אביי, umi amar Abaye, okay, now, ומי אמר אביי רבי מאיר חייש
למיתה? umi amar Abaye Rabbi Meir chayish le'mita? Does Abaye really say
that Rabbi Meir is concerned about death? Because now the way we
have the debate is Rabbi Meir says you can't use this animal
because he is concerned that it will die, right? Because that was
the ברייתא. braita The ברייתא braita? said that it was, what was
the ברייתא? braita. כל דבר שיש בו רוח חיים רבי מאיר אומר,
kol davar she'yesh bo ruach chayim Rabbi Meir omer, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says it's good, and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says כל דבר
שיש בו רוח חיים אינו עושהו לא דופן לסוכה kol davar she'yesh
bo ruach chayim eino osehu lo dofen l'sukkah etc. So רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir is the one that's concerned it will die. רבי יהודה
לא חייש Rabbi Yehuda lo chayish and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, is
not concerned. That's the way we explained that ברייתא. braita, Is that
really true? והתנן, vehatnan, we taught in a משנה, בת ישראל שניסית
לכהן, bat Yisrael she'nisiet l'Kohen, a Jewish woman who's married to a
כהן. Kohen. Because she's married to a כהן, Kohen, she's entitled to
eat תרומה. Trumah. והלך בעלה למדינת הים, vehalach ba'alah l'medinat hayam, her
husband went on an overseas trip. אוכלת בתרומה בחזקת שהוא קיים. ochelet
b'Trumah b'chezkat shehu kayam. She can continue eating תרומה Trumah because, why
isn't she afraid, look, I don't know where my husband is, this
was before the age of telephones and emails, and he might be
dead and I don't know about it. So why can she continue
to eat תרומה? Trumah? Maybe she's no longer the wife of a
כהן. Kohen. No, it's basically a principle of חזקה, chazakah, he left
when he's alive, you consume that he has a חזקת חי. chezkat
chai. If that was his status when he left, then you can
assume that status continues to obtain until you know otherwise. So he's
considered to be alive and she can continue to eat תרומה. Trumah.
One minute, ורמינהי, u'remin'hu, but we then we showed a contradiction to
this or something that seems to contradict it. הרי זה גיטך שעה
אחת קודם מיתתי. harei zeh gittech sha'ah achat kodem mitati. A man
gives a גט to his wife and says, this is your גט
that take effect a minute before I die. The reason to say
that is let's say to save her from having to do יבום
yibum with the brother. Okay, so the minute before you become a
widow, you'll become a divorcee. It'll take effect a minute before I
die. אסורה לאכול בתרומה. asurah l'echol b'Trumah. Now if he's a כהן,
Kohen, she can't eat תרומה. Trumah. Why can't she eat תרומה? Trumah?
Because any minute might be, what might anyone minute be? Any minute
might be the minute before he dies! He might die the next
minute. So at any given minute could be the minute before he
dies, and therefore at any particular time she might be divorced, and
therefore she can't eat תרומה. Trumah. So this seems to be, אסורה
לאכול בתרומה מיד, asurah l'echol b'Trumah miyad, seems to be an exact
parallel case, right? Both cases, wife of a כהן. Kohen. In one
case she can eat תרומה, Trumah, she can assume he's still alive.
In another case she can't eat תרומה, Trumah, she has to be
afraid that he'll die in the next minute. So you can't show
with a ספק, safek, the ספק, safek, right? Right. So are we
concerned that he is going to die or not? What's the story?
אמר אביי, Abaye, Abaye says, לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult.
הא רבי מאיר דלא חייש למיתה, ha Rabbi Meir d'lo chayish le'mita,
the one that says that she can continue eating תרומה Trumah when
her husband is away is רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir who's not concerned
about death. הא רבי יהודה דחייש למיתה, ha Rabbi Yehuda d'chayish le'mita,
the other is רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who is concerned about death.
Where do we see that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda, have this debate? דתניא, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa
הלוקח יין מבין הכותים, halokeach yayin mibein haKutim, somebody who buys wine
from Samaritans. You buying wine from Samaritans, you have to assume that
they have not taken תרומות ומעשרות. Trumot u'ma'asrot. It's even worse than
the case of an עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. By an עם הארץ
am ha'aretz you can assume that he took תרומה Trumah because a
תרומה Trumah is only a tiny bit. By Samaritans you have to
assume they didn't even take תרומה. Trumah. So you have to be
מפריש תרומות ומעשרות. mafrish Trumot u'ma'asrot. Now the point is, it's about
to be שבת, Shabbos let's say. And I mean there's a big
תוספות to figure out some of the exact details, but it's about
to be שבת, Shabbos. and you don't have the time to be
מפריש תרומות ומעשרות. mafrish Trumot u'ma'asrot. So what are you going to
do? Okay, so because it is not, because you know there's some
degree here of a ספק, safek, I mean some degree lenient, it's
not like it's ודאי טבל, vadai tevel, you're suspicious that they didn't
take תרומות ומעשרות, Trumot u'ma'asrot, but it's not like it's ודאי טבל.
vadai tevel. So we give you, you know, so we give you
a little bit of a leniency. So it says like this, although
רש"י does say, I should say רש"י does say הלוקח ממנו צריך
לעשר ודאי ולא דמאי דעל התרומה נחשדו. halokeach mimenu tzarich l'aser vadai
v'lo demai d'al haTrumah nechshadu. So it's not דמאי, demai, it's worse
than דמאי, demai, but even so it's not exactly the same as
straight טבל. tevel. Okay? You don't exactly know the story about this
group, about this. So we give you a little leniency and we
allow you to be מפריש תרומות ומעשרות mafrish Trumot u'ma'asrot without it
being, without it being an actual act of הפרשה. hafrashah. And here's
what you do. So you say the following. שאומר, she'omer, you say,
שני לוגים שאני עתיד להפריש הרי הן תרומה. shnei logim she'ani atid
lehafrish harei hen Trumah. The two לוג log that I will eventually
separate off, then they will be תרומה. Trumah. Meaning I'm not doing
the הפרשה hafrashah now. Now. I'm going to start eating from it
as soon as שבת Shabbos, begins. But on מוצאי שבת Motzoei Shabbos
I will designate two לוג, log, and those two לוג log that
I designate מוצאי שבת Motzoei Shabbos are the two לוג log that
now I am calling תרומה. teruma. So I am now saying that
two לוג log are תרומה. teruma. Which two לוג? log? The two
לוג log to be named later. The two לוג log that I
will identify later, but right now I am making them תרומה. teruma.
עשרה מעשר ראשון, Asara maaser rishon, ten of them are for first
מעשר, maaser, assuming you start with 102 units. So you take off
two units for תרומה, teruma, now you're left with 100 units. So
ten units are מעשר. maaser. תשעה מעשר שני. Tesha maaser sheini. Now
you're left with 90 units. So ten percent of 90 is 9.
So nine more units are now the second מעשר. maaser. ומחל ושותה
מיד. U'mechal v'shoseh miyad. Now what does the word ומחל mechal mean?
It might mean מתחיל. mas'chil. רש"י says ומחל mechal means you're מחלל,
mechalel, you transfer the קדושה kedusha of the מעשר שני maaser sheini
to a coin. And then you begin to drink right away. דברי
רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. That's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says.
So basically, this is a principle you might be familiar with of
ברירה. breira. You're saying something now, but exactly what it refers to
will only be defined based on what you do later. And רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says that's fine. We give you that latitude. We
say יש ברירה. yesh breira. And when you don't have the time
to be מפריש mafrish תרומות ומעשרות terumos u'maasros right now, we let
you do that and get away with it, and then you can
begin using it on שבת. Shabbos Okay, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir. says. רבי יהודה ורבי יוסי ורבי שמעון, Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabbi Yosi
v'Rabbi Shimon, top of עמוד א. ברירה Breira means then you always,
you make stipulations now that you will actualize later? No. It means
that based on how things happen later, that determines what the status
of them was right now. Meaning right now let's hold off for
ברירה, breira, we'll get to it tomorrow. But the basic idea is
right now I am designating something, but it's not identifiable right now,
but it'll be identifiable retroactively based on what happens later. Okay, so
based on what's going to happen in the future, retroactively we'll be
able to say that's what I was referring to at that time.
It's not just something to take place later. That's easier. That's like
to give a גט דחל אחר זמן get d'chal achar zman or
something. This is that what happens later determines what I'm doing right
now. רבי יהודה ורבי יוסי ורבי שמעון אוסרין. Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabbi Yosi
v'Rabbi Shimon osrin. רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יוסי, and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon forbid it. Okay, so now what do we have? So
we're assuming what's the debate of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir. and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda here? So the way אביי Abaye is framing it,
it's not a debate of ברירה breira or not. It's a debate
of are we concerned that, are we concerned that the wine will
all spill out? Okay, because an end of this ברייתא braisa, basically
says, aren't you concerned שמא יבקע הנוד? shema yibaka hanod? Right, aren't
you concerned? It's not here, we'll get to it later, that you
have your wine in these barrels. It's only going to work if
you have wine left over at the end of שבת, Shabbos right?
Only if there's wine left over at the end of שבת Shabbos
retroactively is that the wine I took as תרומות ומעשרות. terumos u'maasros.
Let's say before שבת Shabbos. is over, all the barrels break and
you have no wine left over. Okay, so that would be a
reason to not let you do this trick. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir,
says I'm not concerned about that. Right, as we'll see later in
the ברייתא, they're going to say to him, aren't you concerned that
the barrels will break? And he says you know what, when it
breaks, I'll worry about it. Which means I'm not concerned about it.
Right, so exactly. So אביי Abaye, says what's the debating? They're debating
like this question about מיתה. Are we concerned that somebody will die?
Are we concerned that something unusual like this will happen? רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir isn't concerned. He lets her eat תרומה teruma when the
husband is away on his business trip. רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda who
is concerned that the barrel will break, is also concerned that the
husband will die, and therefore in the case by the גט that
won't let her eat because any minute might be the minute before
the husband dies. So are we concerned he'll die or not is
a debate of רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda
There's only one little problem. That that works out very nicely in
this case of the wine and it explains the contradiction about can
the woman eat תרומה teruma or not. The problem is that in
our case, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir was the one who said I
don't want you to use the animal. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
said I could use the animal. And now we're saying that רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir is the one who's concerned that the husband will
die and is not concerned that the barrel will break and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is concerned. So how what are you going to
do? So let's take a look, let's take a look at what
the גמרא says. איפכא. Ipcha. The גמרא says you gotta like, you
gotta reverse it. It can't be what you just said. It can't
be that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir isn't concerned and and רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda is concerned. You have to say רבי מאיר חייש למיתה,
Rabbi Meir chayish l'misa, רבי יהודה לא חייש למיתה. Rabbi Yehuda lo
chayish l'misa. You gotta reverse it! דתניא, עשאו בהמה דופן לסוכה, asslo
be'eima dofen l'sukkah, רבי מאיר פוטר, Rabbi Meir poteir, רבי יהודה מכשיר.
Rabbi Yehuda machshir. So you got right because we just had that
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says that it's no good to use the
animal, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says it is good. And remember, according
to אביי, Abaye that was based on a concern that it'll die.
And here's the same אביי Abaye that says it's the reverse, that
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir isn't concerned it'll die, that the barrel will
break, and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is concerned. So קשיא דרבי מאיר
אדרבי מאיר. kashya d'Rabbi Meir a'd'Rabbi Meir. So it's a contradiction of
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבי מאיר. In one case he's concerned
that the animal will die, in another case he's concerned he's not
concerned that the barrel will break. גמרא says אמר לך רבי מאיר
amar lach Rebbi Meir no מיתה שכיחא misa shchicha פקיעת נוד לא
שכיחא pkiyos nod lo shchicha אפשר דמסר ליה לשומר. efshar d'masrei lei
l'shomer. No, it's a difference, he says, you know what, it's not
true. I'm concerned that the animal will die, that is a concern
I have. This issue about the about the about the barrel breaking
and why am I not concerned about that? I'm not contradicting myself.
That I'm not concerned about because, you know, you can protect barrels
from breaking more than you can stop people from dying. Wine skin,
right? Isn't it a... Yeah, I'm saying the barrel, but it's a
wine skin, that's right. א נוד, A nod, א נוד a nod
is more like a canteen, right. That's true. Okay, so the גמרא
says... yeah, I was just whatever. Okay, fine. So the גמרא says
like this: קשיא דרבי יהודה אדרבי יהודה. kashya deRebbi Yehuda a'deRebbi Yehuda.
How about רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda contradicting himself? In our case he's
not concerned that the animal will die, and here he is concerned
and doesn't let you that the wine skin, right, that the that
the flask will break and he's not going to let you do
this thing with the wine? So the גמרא says no. טעמא דרבי
יהודה לאו משום דחייש לפקיעת הנוד. taama deRebbi Yehuda lav mishum dechayish
lepkiyos hanod. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda doesn't let you do this thing
with the wine not because he's concerned the barrel will break, he's
not really concerned with that. אלא משום דלית ליה ברירה. ela mishum
delaysa lei breira. It's because he doesn't he doesn't hold of this
whole trick of ברירה breira that what happens later will retroactively determine
it. So the גמרא says, we'll just read a little bit more,
ולא חייש רבי יהודה לפקיעת הנוד? velo chayish Rebbi Yehuda lepkiyos hanod?
How could you say he's not concerned? How could you say his
issue is ברירה, breira, his issue is not that the barrel will
break, that the the wine flask will break? והא מדקתני סיפא, veha
midkatani seifa, at the end of it says exactly that: אמרו לו
לרבי מאיר: amru lo leRebbi Meir: אי אתה מודה שמא יבקע הנוד?
iy ata modeh shema yibaka hanod? Aren't you concerned that the let's
the flask break ונמצא ששותה טבל למפרע venimtsa sheshose tevel lemafrei'a and
he'll wind up having drunk טבל tevel למפרע? lemafrei'a? אמר להו: amar
lahu: לכשיבקע. lichsheyibaka. He said back to them: when it breaks I'll
worry about it. Which means I'm not worried about it. מכלל, michlal,
so you see, דחייש רבי יהודה לפקיעת הנוד, dechayish Rebbi Yehuda lepkiyos
hanod, that his objection is because he's afraid, רבי יהודה's Rebbi Yehuda
objection is that he's afraid that it'll break. So how is it
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda isn't afraid the animal will die and is
afraid that the wine flask will break? Tell me one wine flask
gets all hundred of them will break, there won't be anything left
for the תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'maasros. So the גמרא says no. התם
רבי יהודה הוא דקאמר לרבי מאיר. hasam Rebbi Yehuda hu dek'amar leRebbi
Meir. That was just רבי יהודה's Rebbi Yehuda way of pushing back
at רבי מאיר. He says like this: לדידי, lidi'di, look רבי מאיר,
as far as I'm concerned, לית ליה ברירה. laysa lei breira. I
don't think you can do this at all, I don't hold of
the principle of ברירה. breira. I don't think that just because you
after שבת figure out what you were talking about retroactively it means
that's what you could say you designated before שבת. You can't do
any retroactive games, I disagree with you in principle. אלא אליבא דך,
ela elidach, but I want to but I want to even challenge
you on your own terms. Even according to you, דאית ברירה, de'ish
breira, that you hold you can do this whole retroactive thing, so
and that's why you're allowed somebody to do this thing with the
wine, אי אתה מודה דשמא יבקע הנוד, iy ata modeh desh'shema yibaka
hanod, shouldn't you at least be concerned that the flask will break?
אמר ליה: amar lei: לכשיבקע. lichsheyibaka. He says no, I'll worry about
it when it happens. So what have we said until now? We
have said that according to אביי, Abaye the debate of רבי מאיר
and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda by the using the animal is are
we concerned that the animal will die? The problem is it's the
same אביי that sort of says that there's a debate of רבי
מאיר and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda of are we concerned that, you
know, that the כהן Kohen will die? Are we concerned that the
flask will break? So what the גמרא has now done is it's
tried to sort of bracketed the כהן Kohen case, which we have
to get back to, and it's tried to say that at least
the issue about the flask of wine breaking is not necessarily relevant
because there they seem to have reversed their position, that you could
be concerned the animal will die like רבי מאיר and not concerned
the flask will break because that's easier to protect against. You could
be not concerned the animal will die like רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda,
and still not like the case of the wine and the flask
because you don't hold of this whole idea of retroactive. So the
debate about the wine and the flask is not relevant to the
debate about whether the animal will die or not, okay? ברירה breira
issue, that's a ברירה breira issue, that's something more easy to protect
against. But what we still haven't done is we still have to
go back to the contradiction about the כהן Kohen because now we've
sort of reversed. Now we have רבי מאיר as the one that
is more concerned with death and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda was the
one that's not concerned with death. So maybe that's going to how
we're going to go back and resolve the issue of the כהן,
Kohen, but in the reverse way that אביי initially said. אביי initially
wanted to make the debate of רבי מאיר and רבי יהודה Rebbi
Yehuda about the wine to be a concern of death, but we've
now redefined that. That issue of the wine is not about a
concern of death or breakage, it's a different type of an issue,
it's a ברירה breira issue. So we still have this contradiction about
the כהן's Kohen wife. That might be רבי מאיר רבי יהודה, but
that might be the reverse. That might be the רבי מאיר רבי
יהודה that we have by the סוכה case where רבי מאיר is
the one concerned for death and רבי יהודה is not the one
concerned for death. Okay, so we'll pick up with this גמרא, yes.